We've learned the basic syntax of CSS.
Now, let's build on that knowledge and
style our project.
As we move forward, we'll learn about lots
of selectors, properties, and values.
To start out, we'll style the basic
elements of our site.
If you were following along with our
previous
example, let's delete the style element
that we created,
because it was only for the purposes of
the example.
We won't need that code in our actual
project.
Next let's create a stylesheet.
So we'll create a new file by right
clicking on the file tree.
And we'll call it main.css.
But you can call yours whatever you'd
like.
As long as it has the .css file
extension and you remember what you called
it.
Now, once I create the file, you'll notice
that it automatically opens it up for me.
But first, we need to move this into our
CSS
directory, so I'm going to click and drag
it into CSS.
There we go.
And before we get started coding over here
in main.css,
we want to make sure that we add this to
our HTML file.
So, this is going to be very similar to
our previous line of CSS.
I'm going to copy that and paste it below,
so I've copied the normalize.css line
here, and I've pasted it below.
And I need to change the filename here to
main.css.
And I'm going to go ahead and
save that.
Because of the cascading nature of CSS,
it's important that our CSS, or main.css,
comes
after normalize.css.
We don't want normalize
to overwrite any of our CSS.
And conversely, we want
to make sure that normalize comes first
and sets up a solid
foundation for our custom CSS.
In fact, we might be overriding
some rules in normalize.css.
So we want main to come after normalize.
That's very important.
Now let's jump into our CSS document,
which I've called main.css.
And let's try a really dramatic and
obvious change, just to make sure
that our CSS is included properly.
I'm going to select the body element,
which is basically the entire page,
and I'm going to change the background
color to orange.
So, I'll type background-color and change
it to orange.
If we save the file and refresh our
preview, you can
see that the background for the entire
page has been changed to orange.
So we know that main.css has indeed been
included properly into our HTML file.
If, for some reason, your background color
doesn't change
to orange, make sure to first check the
syntax here.
And then also check
to make sure that main.css comes after
normalize, and
that the path is correct.
It needs to be the CSS folder
and then main.css, and your main.css file
needs to be inside the CSS folder.
It's very important
as well.
Now, I don't want my body background color
to be orange, so I've highlighted
everything by hitting Cmd+A on a Mac,
or Ctrl+A if you're on Windows, and I'll
delete everything in the file.
Now, I want to remove the underline that's
on our
links, I want to have links that don't
have an underline.
So I'm going to select all of the anchor
elements on our page, and I'm going
to type the property text-decoration and
set it to none.
And if I save that, go back to the
browser, and refresh.
You'll see that first, our background
color has, once again, defaulted
to white, and there are no longer any
underlines on our links.
Great, now let's start organizing our
layout a little bit.
We need to add some markup in order
to wrap the main part of our content and
select it appropriately.
To do that, we're first going to switch
back over to our HTML and create an
element called a div, which doesn't have
any semantic meaning at all.
Rather it's a way for us to encapsulate or
divide a group of elements.
Let's open our div right
after our header element.
So we'll go here, in between
our header and section, we'll type div,
and then we're going to close this
just between our footer and body here.
And you'll notice that work spaces has
actually highlighted body and html in red.
That's because it's
saying, somewhere in here, there's a tag
that is not closed.
And in our case, that's the div.
And if we type that in, you'll see that it
automatically closes for us.
Now we have a lot
of code that needs to be indented by one
tab.
So, starting at the footer down here at
the bottom, going all the way up
to my section here, just before this dig.
I'm going to select everything.
And to do that, I just hold down Shift and
click right here.
Then again, to indent on a Mac, I'm
going to hit Cmd and then closing square
bracket.
And on Windows, you hit Ctrl and square
bracket, and that will indent everything
by one.
So now it's indented by one tab over from
our
div, and that will help to keep our code
organized.
You'll notice that we also have some more
line wrapping going on here, but that's
perfectly fine,
that doesn't effect the functionality of
the code.
Now, we will probably have many divs on
the page, so
we need to identify this div more
specifically according to its function.
So inside of our opening div tag right
here, I'm going to type a space,
and then I'm gonna add an attribute called
id to identify it.
And
I'm going to name this id wrapper.
And I can go ahead and name this whatever
I want, just like I
can type anything into an alt attribute,
or anything into a source or href
attribute.
So I've called this div wrapper, and an id
attribute will
uniquely identify elements on the page.
So now if we save this and
switch over to our CSS, we can go ahead
and type a
hash or a pound symbol, followed by the
name of the id.
So we've called it wrapper, and then we
can go ahead and open up
our curly braces, and that's going to
select that div that we just created.