[MUSIC]
I'm sure you're eager to start writing
your own CSS.
At this point, our website just looks very
plain.
However, it will be much easier for us to
learn how
to use CSS if we get a little bit of
background first.
CSS is an initialism that stands for
Cascading Style Sheets.
The style sheet portion of this term is
obvious.
It just means a document that describes
the visual look of a webpage.
The cascading portion of this term is the
important lesson here.
Each CSS rule has the potential to
override or cancel out previous rules.
Let's take a look at a simple example.
I'm going to add some style tags to our
HTML.
We'll delete these later on and use an
external style sheet instead.
This is just for the purposes of this
example.
So, inside of my head, just after the line
for normalize.css I'm going to open up
some style tags.
And inside, I'm going to type the element
selector footer, open up some curly braces
and inside I'm going to type the color
property followed by the value green.
So,
if you're following along, go ahead and
type that in.
And, we'll go over each part of the syntax
momentarily.
But for now, all you need to know is that
this piece
of CSS code will change the color of our
footer text to green.
So, let's go ahead and save this.
Open up our preview.
Refresh the page and
we'll scroll down to the bottom.
And as you can see, the text here in our
footer is now green.
Now, let's go back to our code and right
underneath.
Let's add another piece of CSS, and we'll
select our footer again.
And we'll do the same thing, only this
time, we'll set the text color to orange.
Now, we have two CSS rules, one right
after another.
The first one changes the paragraph text
to green
and the second one changes the paragraph
to orange.
So then will the text be green?
Because after
all that's the first rule that we applied.
Or will the text be orange?
Let's refresh and find out.
So I'm going to go back here to my
preview.
Refresh the page.
And as you can see our footer text is now
orange.
That's because the second rule has
overwritten the first rule.
Because it comes
later on in the code.
Maybe this seems obvious, but as we code
up lots of CSS,
it's very important to keep this
fundamental cascading rule set in mind.
Sometimes it can cause strange problems
that are very difficult to resolve.
But if you're very careful about
understanding how
your CSS cascades, then it will be much
easier.
In fact, as we
build our project, There will be many
instances where
we use the cascading nature of CSS to our
advantage.
We've already discussed the syntax of CSS
in previous videos,
but it's important that the syntax becomes
second nature to you.
So let's review again.
Now I'm going to remove this second rule,
and just focus on one rule at a time.
This entire piece of code, the element
selector, the property, the
value, the curly braces.
All of this is called a rule.
We will create many CSS rules in our
project.
The first portion of this rule that says
footer is
called a selector because it tells the
browser which element
on the page we want to apply our styling
to.
This particular selector is called an
element selector, because
it's selecting based on the name of the
element.
And in this case, our element is named
footer.
There are many other types of selectors
that can narrow
down our styling to more specific parts of
the page.
We'll learn about lots of selectors
throughout the course of this project.
Next are the curly braces which
encapsulate which kinds of styling
we want to be applied to whatever has been
selected in our selector.
Inside of our curly braces, we have a line
of CSS.
And this entire line is called a
declaration
because we're basically declaring or
saying that
we want some kind of styling applied.
A CSS rule could include multiple
declarations.
But in this case we have just one the
first
part of the declaration right here is
called a property.
In this case we're using the color
property
which changes the color of text after the
property is a colon
and then a value followed by a semicolon
which
ends the declaration.
The value in this case is green.
And once again you can go ahead and hover
over a color in workspaces.
To see a preview
of what that color looks like.
So let's review backwards.
We have a property and value pair here
which makes a declaration.
We can have several of these declarations
that live inside of these curly braces.
The curly braces encapsulate which
declarations
should be applied to the selector.
All of that stuff together is called a
rule.
As we use these terms in practice, they'll
become more familiar to you.
This is important because it will be
easier for
you to listen and discuss with other
designers and developers.
Let's try a few more examples before we
jump into a quiz.
Let's jump inside of our rule here and add
another declaration
that will change the background color.
This is different from the text
color and we'll mean to use another CSS
property, so let's try it out.
I'm going to use the background-color
property.
And you'll notice that once again,
Workspaces uses
code completion to suggest a property to
us.
And then, it also uses code completion to
suggest a value.
However there are other values,
other than the ones listed here that we
can type.
I'm going to change our background color
to orange.
And then I'm going to change the text
color to white.
Now of course our webpage has a white
background.
So in order to see the text, we'll
need a separate background color like
we've done here.
Now, let's go ahead and save and
refresh our preview here.
And down at the bottom you can see that we
now have an orange background
color for the entirety of the footer,
which spans the entire width of the page.
And then the text color is now white.
But, what if we wanted to apply this to
another element instead of the footer?
Let's say that this is what we wanted
our navigation to look like.
Well, we could go back to our code
and change the selector from footer to nav
because we have our nav element further
down the page, right here.
So, let's go ahead and save, go back to
our preview, and scroll to the top,
and when we refresh the page, you can see
that this styling has now been applied
to our navigation.
And has been removed from our footer.
Now, the background color is orange but,
as you can see,
the links are still the default color that
the browser has applied.
So, any links that have already been
clicked
are purple, and any links that have not
been clicked are blue.
So why didn't this text change to white?
Well, this is a problem that's called
selector specificity.
In this case, the browser is applying a
default selector that's lightly more
specific than ours.
We're just saying that we want to
apply this to the navigation.
But the browser has gotten more specific
and styled the anchor tags.
So, we need to, in
turn, get even more specific than the
browser to describe what we mean here.
So, let's go ahead and jump back into our
code.
And let's modify the selector int what's
called a descendant selector.
We want to specifically select the anchor
elements that are inside of the nav.
So, here we have nav then an unordered
list.
A list item, and then an anchor element.
However, we don't need to include these
other elements, we
can just jump straight down to the anchor
from our nav.
So what does that
look like?
Well we have our nav here, that's already
selected.
And right now this is an element selector.
To make this a descendant selector we
follow up nav with a space, and
then type a so this looks very similar to
our element
selector, but now this is a new selector
that will select the anchor elements.
Inside of our nav
so it's going down the tree here in our
HTML from nav down to anchor.
So let's go ahead and save the page.
And refresh here to see what this looks
like.
As you can see our styling has now been
applied to the individual links
inside of our navigation.
So, no longer is the nav element what's
being styled here, we're actually
selecting the specific anchor elements.
So, the nav background has now defaulted
back to white.
But our nav links now have that orange
background and the white text color.
All right, I think we've done enough
practice exercises to get us started.
We're ready to jump into coding the CSS
for our project.